foreign
it's September 15 2023 and we're at the
Active inference Institute in active
guest stream number 56.1 today we have
Gregory Sergeant Petri
and we'll be hearing a talk followed by
a discussion on Geometry of world model
influences behaviors
first there'll be a presentation and
then any comments that people have in
the live chat
or any other questions it'll be great to
talk so thank you a lot for coming
really looking forward to this so peace
to you
May thank you very much Daniel for the
invitation first it's really I'm very
happy to to be able to present this this
work here so it's a it's a work around
the like some models uh
of Consciousness at least some some
computational models of Consciousness
some part of Consciousness and how it
can help to generate a different kind of
behaviors especially when we
let's think about let's say
artificial agents so it's a um it's a
work in collaboration with uh so David
Davidoff Kenneth Williams
in fact it's a it's not just one work
it's a collection of of works that been
have been on for like uh already around
10 years so if you want to know more
about like this group and the work that
we're doing you can go on the page on my
personal webpage and there's a link to
PCM dot HTML and there's a summary of
all the work we've been doing and some
uh
summary of the work we've been doing and
also of some articles that can be
relevant on this subject so today we'll
focus more particularly on two uh two
articles so one that is accepted and
will appear very soon the other one need
to resubmit which uh give formulation of
let's say autonomous agents or like
let's say
mathematical formulation of agents that
have a world model that is structured
geometrically in such a way that this
world model captures some features of
Consciousness so the first article is
let's say the
that we we view all the experimental
results that we have and the like most
recent formalism that we have on our
work which is
to the literature on pomd partially
terrible monitoring process which is
optimal control stochastic optimal
control and we just try to tweak a bit
and this formalism to uh introduce the
ideas with how you can include inside of
the world model of the agent some ideas
on Consciousness and still continue to
have algorithms to do inference to find
Optimal policies and everything and the
second article focuses more particularly
on how uh changing the world model of
the agents can change its behavior in
particularly the relationship the
geometry of the world model the way that
it perceives Etc and the way it acts
with respect to uh for agent strategy so
the way that it looks for something so
it will change its behavior and looking
for something so I will start by
presenting a bit what uh what are all
these terms or World model what you
needed what it is what is a foraging
strategy what it is to how you how can
you define an agent that is looking for
a certain object in particular what is
an exploration based on curiosity or say
more technically epistemic value
so let's consider the setting where you
have a let's say a real world so it's a
space that surround us through each
space you do a setup where you have an
agent which is let's say a solid it has
a solid frame so it has a center of
three axis but it's in front but it's on
its side where it's above above it and
it's looking for an object o which is
itself a solid inside of R3 and all the
configuration of the agents and the
objects they are defined by let's say a
reference frame that is a external and
that the that characterizes completely
their configuration inside of this world
now the agent a
what it wants to do is to find for the
object o but it doesn't it can only have
like some noisy observation of where the
object o is so to be able to find all it
needs to have some
a priorian world o should be
to be able to plan the consequences of
its actions with respect to where or
will be once it has moved and to update
and to be able to plan what
the how the observation can act with
respect to updating its prior so in
other words so you have have an agent
and the agent is looking for oh and
things that always for example in this
direction on the right so it's going to
move towards the right and makes an
observation if it doesn't CEO it's going
to change its belief on where o is so
this is a very standard formalism that
you can find like in pomdp stochastic
optimal control
but the one other point we want to to to
Really emphasize is the fact that the
agent a has its own frame of reference
in the way that it's going to give the
coordinates coordinates of the object
the way that it will Trace worthy object
is is using its own way of computing the
the coordinates of O so it has its own
way to measure where o is so it doesn't
have to refer to a global frame a global
coordinate system to be able to know
where o is so for example I am always
centered on myself when I move I see the
object I I don't think about me moving
but I think about the object moving and
this is because when I move I change my
frame so the way I'm going to reference
the object is going to change
accordingly and the point we want to
introduce is the fact that you can have
several ways of defining for the agent
to Define its own coordinate system with
respect to its environment and this is a
key feature of that we want to capture
like in terms of of modeling but that's
also wishing that it is something that
is very structuring with respect to
models of Consciousness because when you
consider like more generally an agent
uh
that that had that is let's say that has
a world model uh on in which it has its
own let's say uh it has its own point of
view perspective on this world model you
kind of have to start tackling the the
problem of how to introduce a point of
view on the environment of the agent how
can you introduce in the way that it's
uh it is going to encode its environment
a certain point of view and in
particular if you think like about it in
terms of the role of space to be able to
take into account your own perspective
on the environment you can see that if
you take away this like everything that
fills up the space you keep just the
space itself
it's it's uh the space allows you to uh
let's say to structure the way that you
are going to fill in some informations
about the environment and it's centered
on your own point of view in a way that
when you're going to act you're still
going to keep this still says this the
the like the unfilled space the St you
you're still going to keep the stay same
way of modeling this space the space
will stay the same when you move
when I move the space is the same but I
talk into account the fact that I can
move from one point to another in this
space without changing the space and
something that is also very important is
that with respect to any movement that I
can do the space doesn't change so
there's no particular point in space
with respect to the movements that I do
another way another property that is
very similar is that instead of
considering just my actions and the way
that I can change my frame while I'm
doing an action you can also Imagine
taking the frame of somebody else so it
means that you can you see that the
space that you you use to be able to
structure your environment doesn't
change when you take the perspective of
somebody else for example if you imagine
yourself as a solid agent changing by
your rotation your own like coordinates
your own solid frame and translating
okay so this is uh something that we
will use in fact as a definition for the
state space the the way that the agent
encodes its environment and we will see
that there's a natural notion to be able
to that encodes this idea that you can
change perspective on your environment
on the world model that you have of your
environment simply by introducing
something that's very well known which
is the notion of a group acting under a
certain space so this is just to sum up
a bit the what we're trying to do so
we're just trying trying to do like
exploration inside of an environment but
we're adding an additional information
which is that the way the agents is
going to encode its environment takes
into consideration the fact that it can
change its reference frame on this space
without singling out any point
okay so what do you mean like
perspective taking in like more
precisely so how do we go from The Real
World so the let's say the world and
code the world described by the external
like a frame that allows you to say the
agent is here and the object is here
from the internal world to of the agents
so you just Define the map that will
take into consideration that the agent
can have a first perspective on this
environment the simplest case in the
occasion case is just rewriting the
coordinates a bow inside of the frame of
the agent reference rate of the agent
and then once the agent moves its frame
solid frame in the real world changes
and this induces indeed the
transformation inside of its internal
World which will be in a fine
transformation
okay but you could imagine also having
other Transformations I don't know if
you can see my my mouse
probably can you see my mouse or not no
okay so okay so the map C PSI can also
be
something else than a defined
transformation it could be like any kind
of transformation for example in a fine
case the apparent volume of the object
doesn't change but if you change this
map and consider for example the
projective transformation
as we will describe later you can add
that the size apparent size of the
object changes so we we went from
something that is a bit like already
like very well known and not not very
Innovative which is that you can rewrite
like motions depend like the emotions
depends on the way it depends on the
frame that you choose to describe them
into seeing that you can in fact change
some frames to be able to account for
some uh like perceptive property
and what we asked also for the agents
that we consider is that they can
imagine the consequences of their moves
which on their uh future observations
so there's something just to say that
the agents that we consider have a
notion of agency which is that they can
plan the consequences of their actions
so that they can choose the best action
with respect to a certain reward in
particular the reward that we consider
is the trying to maximize a certain
surprise
so to sum it up we have an agent that is
looking for certain objects so it has
belief of where the subject is and the
beliefs lives on on an internal State
space so the world model of the
environment
it can make observation which allows it
to update uh its beliefs and then it can
predict the consequences of its actions
so that it can plan the way that it
should act with respect to a certain
objective so formally this is simply the
notion of markup decision process or
more generally like notion of partially
observable markup decision process
because we do not have a complete
information of the environment but also
but only some observations that are that
are limited and uh it's very related and
let's say
I mean
there's a strong Duality between Po mdp
and active inference so there's really a
strong link between both
so
now what I did in the way that I
presented it so I presented it with the
idea I tried to present the idea of what
we're doing so the general context
pomdps agents that are planning uh their
action with respect to certain objective
here the objective is to find a certain
object
and uh I give uh the formal setting for
defining it which are ndpmvpn now I will
go one step further and Define it
explicitly and I will continue like this
approach for the second part where I
will also present our results and our
specificity where else developed with
the general statement then a bit more
precise and then really digging digging
into the result so here the classical
way to define the markup decision
process is to consider that you have a
set of configurations of the environment
which is the state space of the world
model in the way and at least the way
that you encode your environment so this
is something on which you can act
because the agent when it makes an
action it changes the state of the
environment
and the actions the way that the actions
change the environment is with respect
to a certain uh
Markov kernel
probability kernel so it's stochastic
which means that each actions changes
the state of the environment but you
don't know completely I guess not
deterministic it you allow some errors
in the way that it acts on the
environment
and you have a reward form a function
that is associated to the actions that
you can do at 20 and also the state of
the the agent that time t and partial
observable partially observable markup
decision process is the same thing that
a markup decision process
but you authorize to say that your
observation on your environment are only
partial which means that you do not have
a pre-say precise information on the
states of the environment so the way
that you need to relate observation and
states is through also a probability
kernel which tells you that
uh if you're at state for example s
you would expect to make a certain
observation let's say of if you if you
think the object is at The X
you expect to see the object attacks but
with a certain error because you know
that your sensors are also random they
have some they have they can make some
mistakes
and you keep similarly a reward function
so it's the same thing that an mdp
Markov decision process but usually also
allow to have some
to get information on your environment
through observations that are not
complete
in fact there's a formulation in terms
of partially observable markup decision
processes our particular case of markup
decision processes which is called
belief Markov and belief and DPS Billy
markov's decision process
and the only difference that you have
between Minecraft process and belief mdp
is the fact that the state space is
necessarily continuous in the second
case so po ndps can be seen as a
particular place of ndps
so
we said that the actions of a pomdp act
on the state space and you have you
account for the consequences of the
actions only through observations so
graphically it means that you have the
state space of your so the world model
your environment X
on which you you like you reference for
example where the object is so the
position of the object
and then when you act it induces a
consequence on the position of the
objects at time t plus one and then you
can make an observation of who you think
the object will be or you can make an
observation with respect to where the
object is depending if you're planning
into the future or if you're really
doing the action uh you're you're
implementing the consequence of the
actions in the real world
the thing that we're trying to do in our
setting is to replace simply the actions
by a change of perspective like I told
you like when the agent asks it's
coordinate system on the environment
changes so you can always see it as in a
way passively where you just see it as a
change of coordinates so we want to say
that instead of considering actions on
the environment we have a space on which
there's a natural notion of changing of
reference frame and actions are simply
certain kind of changes of frames we
also allowed to have some actions that
are do not correspond to changes of
frames we just say that we include the
possibility that some actions are
changes of frames and the changes or
frames are have something that is
related to all the Transformations that
are internal at the for the agents so
for example things that it knows that a
priori it knows it's encoded in the way
the agents will interact with the
environment
so
the way that we do it a bit more
formally is that we say that changing
perspective is simply through the action
of a group
so for example in the affine case when
the the agents
moves it changes a frame is a defined
transformation and we say that the world
model so the state space is simply a
space on which the group acts so
formally
what does it mean that the group acts on
the space is just saying that
you for you have space s
and Group G there's an application that
goes that takes an element from G and S
and that sends back s in other words for
every GI you can associate a function
from S2s and you assume well so that it
has good properties which is that it
satisfies equation one and that uh if
you don't move you stay at the same
place
so this is like just the notion of a g
space a space a group acting on the
space but now if we want to include this
in
ndps and P1 DPS we just assume that
the state space is a g space that some
actions are some elements of the group
and that when we choose the actions that
corresponds to the element of the group
that corresponds to the way that the
group acts on the element so it's very
like there's nothing like very
convoluted it's just saying that you
define a collection of functions which
you see as changes of frames and the way
that they act so the probability kernel
from the state space to the States
states that time T2 time t plus one
after reaction
uh after the change of perspective is
simply through the way that the function
changes the state space
so it's just kind of a way of
reformulation but what is really hidden
behind here is that we have the
structure of the group
and that we don't consider any kind of
actions we assume that there is more
structure in the actions that we can
consider and then it's defined that is
that it's uh in like in the way that is
uh it's that it's encoded inside of the
geometry of the space that we have so we
don't separate any more action and state
space we say that the state space in its
geometry encodes already certain kind of
actions which are the change of
perspectives so there are two cases that
we consider the first case is where the
status is The Arcadian space and gdfn
transformation it corresponds to like I
find Transformations translations and
rotations of the agents and changing
rewriting the coordinates of the objects
inside of the ref solid reference frame
of the agent and the second case where
uh the first the state spaces the
projected space and the group is a
projected transformation
we described how what are the generative
models that we consider and how we can
include so the inside of the classical
theory of pomdps the fact that you can
take a perspective inside on your world
uh on your on your environment now we
will introduce uh like a classical
notion of epistemic value which will
allow us to Define what is uh Behavior
what is an exploratory Behavior with
respect to curiosity so how what it is
foreign agent 2 uh exploits an
environment based on curiosity
so
curiosity or let's say the drive for
exploration
is uh
uh quantity that will it's a it's a
quantity that you will
um
Okay so
it's uh
okay it's
so how do you define it just with like
very generally
so you start with the agent has a prior
on the state of its environments then it
plans the consequence of one of its move
step so this changes the prior that it
has on the environment because there's
action on the environment so we get a
new prior
and now it's going to make an
observation once so it imagines that
it's going to make an observation once
it makes an observation it's there's an
aposteri the priorities of data so you
get an Apple Theory the way that you
Define curiosity or let's say epistemic
value is how informative is the
observation that you will do how far is
the apostillary from the apiary but this
you cannot do it for one given
observation because the way that you
compute It Is by planning what will
happen at the next step so you need to
consider all the possible observation
that you will make so the observations
are themselves stochastic with respect
to the way that you consider which is
actually a priori on the state space of
a Time t
as we said
for us actions are changing the frame so
we can also Define epistemic value four
frames for changes of frames and in
particular something that we gain that
is I think interesting is that now we
have a function that is defined on the
on the group that can be a continuous
group so you can allows you have for
example if you want to maximize it you
you can or minimize it and it depends
how you see it you can watch you you
couldn't do gradient descent for example
so you can have more analytical tools
because you're on the space that is
continuous and has some structure
so now to give the formal definition of
epistemic value so as I said
it's based on the quantity c c that I
will Define now
so if you have yourself if you give
yourself a prior on a space X and you
give yourself a probability kernel so
stochastic map from X to Y stochastic
map is simply saying that for any X you
will associate the measure on y
then you can get a joint Distribution on
X and Y which is simply given by the
product p y doing x times the prior
in fact the quantity C is simply the
mutual information between X and Y
which is saying how far is the joint
distribution with respect to the uh the
independent distribution the product of
the marginal distribution next and on y
but this is like you you see it it
appears everywhere the mutual
information so this formulation is based
on the paper that is uh from a fist on
the null active inference and a pessimic
value the mutual information is
something that appears everywhere but I
think that there's a very nice
re-expression of the mutual information
which allows to give a better
interpretation of this quantity and
which is the interpretation I was
discussing in the previous slide so if
you rewrite Mutual information you can
always see it as the coolback library
distance between the posteriorly for a
given observation and the prior pullback
distance being a way of computing how
far you are how far the two distribution
are but you need to look at the
expectation with respect to the
observation that you make so it's
exactly what I was discussing before
so then uh
uh this is like for any kernel any
kernel from X from y x to Y with a prior
on x
but as we were discussing here you have
to take into con so this would be the
kernel but you have to take into
consideration that you can do actions
and let your prior r on X so the way to
the compute epistemic value in for this
kernel here
when having only your the prior on X is
that you propagate the prior buy the
action on X1 then you get the prior on
X1 and you can Define the epistemic
value for this prior and Markov kernel
which responds to like the randomness of
your sensors which is always fixed and
this is very important this one doesn't
change even if you change frames the
kernel that you have relating your prior
what you think about the state space so
relating the state space and the
observation never changes
and so
especially this means that we after a
certain action or after a certain change
of frame and get a joint Distribution on
X and Y which is the following one here
so this corresponds to the prior
propagated on X1
and then the epistemic value is simply
the neutral information of this joint
distribution so now how does the
algorithm work the algorithm that
corresponds to uh defining an
exploratory behavior for an agent that
is looking for
so he said it started with a prior of
where o should be then you maximize
curiosity based on some changes of
frames that are around the identity
Elements which correspond to not
changing frame
then you get an action that you can
apply you propagate the prior to the
next step with this action and then you
just update your priori with respect to
a certain observation
and then it Loops back so this is the
algorithm that we consider uh
in the second paper that I that was
listed in the in the presentation so
which corresponds to having an agent
that is looking for a certain object is
it's um behavior is defined by an
exploratory is is driven by exploration
uh driven by curiosity taking into
account that its state space is
structured by the action of a group so
that the state space is structured by
the fact that it it corresponds to all
the possible ways of like changing
frames so it has inside of the state
space inside of the geometry of the
state space all the possible ways of
changing frames
uh
and uh this is this is like explicitly
what we do so I mean in this context
this is the algorithm that we consider
and nothing else
then we get a very interesting result at
least I find I mean it's not it's
interesting and like in the way that
it's presented here I find it
interesting and then I mean if you go
more into detail and it's it's because
the occlusion case is very particular
but
what you get is that if you look at the
behavior of an agent that is driven by
exploration by curiosity uh
but that has a state space structured by
occlusion transformation or clearing
transformation so the first case where
the agent is simply
uh encoding its environment in its
reference frame but nothing else
then it doesn't need to move
in the second case where the changes of
charts are given by projective
Transformations so the way it encodes to
it's in transformation
they take to account a perspective a
projective uh deformation of its
environment then it will always try to
get closer to the object so you have two
very separate behaviors so this is
something that is
I think it's a very interesting to to
note
so before going into the details of uh
how you can improve the statement
I will say a bit more about why it's
more it's an interesting perspective
point of view on the on the subject
because and how it goes a bit further
than simply considering this very simple
setting
what you could imagine is that encoding
the fact that the agent encoding the
actions of the agent directly inside of
the state space of the Asian through
geometry could be a way to stabilize the
representations of the agent
and this is something that we're working
on now
and there's already already literature
in this direction
okay
so now let us proof uh the statements
and to prove the statement we need to
give a formal like a precise uh
statement
so what more particularly what we were
able to show is that if you assume that
the agent has us move staying still so
it's allowed to stay still
then if uh it's it's uh changes of frame
are given by actually by a fine
transformation
the agent stays still
now
in the projective case
if you assume that the agent is always
looking in the direction of the object
it will always try to get closer to the
object
okay so the idea of the proof is that
in the what what place the the role for
discriminate for for the tribe of the
agent is how big the agent is appearing
to in the reference how is the size of
the object in the reference frame of the
agent
and it's how big it is it appears to be
to the agent so in the first case the
volume of the object in the internal
space of the agent doesn't change so it
doesn't need to move
in the second case if it makes a move
what is informative is to try to make
the object bigger because once it's
bigger the apostillary will be further
from the prior with respect to a certain
observation so it will always privilege
moves that allow to make the object look
bigger
and in this case what you can do is
um
uh you can you can show that this
corresponds in fact two actions or
change of frames that gets you closer to
the object
okay so how to improve the results
so as we said we consider a change of
frame from The Real World to the
internal World here I didn't consider
changes of perspectives with respect to
moves here is simply how you relate the
real world to the internal world in the
euclidean case it's clear it's clear
it's just the way that you write the
coordinates of the object in the solid
frame in the projected case is clearly
not it's not obvious
because there are several ways that you
can relate the solid frame of the agent
to the projective frame
so one way that we decided to do it
is we give some set of actions that we
consider to Media let's say uh coherent
with our own experience of space
which is that we feel that we're always
centered on ourselves that the access of
the site frame of the agents inside of
the like 3D space so what is in front of
it or what is on the right where the
stops are preserved that there's no
point in front of the object that
appears to be at Infinity
and that that near to the center of the
object the volumes are preserves
so when you do this so this uh this
formulation like this result is in in
this article here
so the way that we relate Some solid
frames like some solid referencement of
the agent to some protective
Transformations are in this article in
particularly in proposition A1 where we
show that this set of actions limits
the set of projective transformation we
can consider and we will only have this
projected transformation
and so the change of frames from the
external world to the internal world is
given by rewriting the coordinates of
the agent of the object in the solid
stream of the agent and then applying
this projective transformation
so now uh what we defined here is are
the maps that relate the observation of
the agents
Zach
so the we we defined the maps in the
occlusion and projective case that
relate the observation of the agent the
observation of the object to the way
that it represents this this object
inside of its internal world
here
so
this is simply like the pomdp
that we defined before and now once the
agent doesn't move it changes its
equation reference frame so there is a
solid reference frame so that from going
from one side reference frame to another
side reference frame you can by applying
the projective transformation we had
before Define another one that we call
PSI that goes from the state space at
Time Zero to the state space after
action after moving very what is very
important is that we consider uh the
Markov kernel Associated to a noisy
observation to be of this shape here
which is that if you know about the
object if you think the object is at
point x then you believe that the
observation will be around X in the ball
uh around X for a ball of a certain
radius which is a small ranges Epsilon
okay and I need to charge my computer so
sorry
okay
so now press uh epic value as defined
um
it
has a very simple expression
so the epistemic value of the prior
propagated after the transformation Phi
after this changes of frame five so you
have a problem here you propagate it on
X1 through Phi and you compute the
epistemic value for this uh for the
joint distribution over X1 and Y is
given by this formula here well it's
simply integrating over all the possible
places where the object could be times
the
probabilistic volume of the ball
um
of size that sit on uh for the
propagated measure and the logarithmic
of the sequentity okay so this is very
direct to write you can just compute it
and you find this expression but what
you have already here is that if you
consider an oxygen transformation then
the quantity Cube sine minus one B
Epsilon y doesn't change
so then you have the sigmatic value that
is a that is constants so basically if
you try to maximize the systemic value
maximize this quantity you can do
anything you have always one move which
is not which is not to move so you don't
move it's okay it's perfectly fine
now in the second case we have the
projective where you consider that the
way you relate environment and the
internal world is through a projective
transformation then it's more
complicated and so you need to uh
use a trick which is that you know that
once an observation has been made the
support of the prior will be smaller
and so after one step if you suppose
that your Epsilon so the size of let's
say noisiness of your sensor is small
enough
you have a support that is uh of the
distribution that sufficient is small
enough so that you can do an asymptotic
development of the quantity in the
integral
so this is an equality but this is an
approximation here
and now this is very useful because now
that you know we're like doing this in a
way uh you can say that you just need to
develop this quantity at the point where
the object is really
so if you do it you get this expression
here
and what appears to play a role is only
the determinant of uh the Jacobian or
the projective transformation which here
in the case will be one
can be many things
so here also is not very clear because
how do you define CM so cm is defined as
a composition of several Maps I didn't
go into the details but it's corresponds
to the map that are given by the changes
of frame so
if you have the oxygen space and the
internal spaces
after moving you have a change of frame
in the equation space but it corresponds
to also a change of frame in the
internal space
so if you the way you define PSI is
simply saying that you inverse the
projective transformation from internal
world to external world to go at Time
Zero then you apply the change of frames
and then you apply the projective
transformation to go from external to
internal
foreign
this formula that you have here
and which is very nice with this and
then you have the first term that
doesn't depend on the actions that you
do so you don't need to take it into
account this one will be one and then
you just need to compute this one
in fact this one has a very simple
expression so it's expression 20 23 and
then here you can directly see which
moves correspond to increasing this
quantity and then decreasing this
quantity
because we want to increase epistemic
value and so this this is the result
this allows to prove the result that we
we said in the first day like in the
several slides before that in the
projective case if you have enough
movements if you look at the object then
you're always going to go closer to the
object
the way to interpret it is as if the
agent it was a bit paranoiac or paranoid
if it's like I'm very uncertain on its
own beliefs so
it knows the object might be over there
but it's always uncertain so it needs to
go check and once I check it's more
certain but still as it can always be
even more certain it will always try to
get more and more certainty
and so I only presented like in this uh
in this presentation all the aspects
which are more computational and what
the algorithm and some like analysis of
the algorithm we considered but we also
have like some experiments on how this
setting can allowed to generate
different behaviors behaviors that we
would expect explain for example some
Illusions like the moon Illusions and
then invite you if you're interested on
this to listen on to the like online
talk
moc-4 conference that was in Oxford last
week or to check up check out one of
these three papers
and I would like to thank you very much
for your attention
all right awesome wow
very interesting and different ways than
how I've seen the
pomdp and related uh
works so
okay let's just start off with little
context and then I'll read some
questions and read some questions from
live chat so what what brought you to
study this question this way
uh what question the question of uh okay
did you come from a math side and find
Consciousness and and geometries to be
interesting or vice versa what kind of
brought you to want to make this
contribution
so at the beginning so when I did my my
uh PhD in maths I was more interested I
was interested in let's say uh like all
this idea of critical critical brain
hypothesis so uh the way that the trying
to understand the way that the brain
processes information and makes it
something that is uh like exploited
and so they one of so the critical brain
hypothesis tells you that the activity
of the neurons is basically close to
certain criticality criticality in the
source of statistical physics if because
you can model the activation of the
neurons as let's say uh statistical
system like an icing model but the so I
worked a lot on this and then I there's
another hypothesis that is uh like very
common which is the Bison brain
hypothesis
and so the Bayesian brain hypothesis led
me to active influence to learning more
about optimal control by Asian fashion
perspective on optimal control
and uh there was uh so uh my advisor was
a PhD advisor was working with David and
they're still together on uh trying to
uh Implement uh some aspects of
consciousness
uh and how it can influence influence
especially with their article in the
Moon Illusion so uh I was interested in
knowing how uh how uh this uh kind of
let's say uh ideas
uh simply like in a very naive way they
interact with the Bison brain hypothesis
and then I continued in fact like one of
the lines of my research is structured
like algebraically structured statistics
or machine learning and so the way that
they see it like very geometrically in
fact or let's say geometrically or
algebraic it's not the same thing but
it's very related it's something that I
I wanted to uh to to understand a bit
better let's set you to make it in a
formal setting so that it's simply a
particular case of what are what is in
the literature so it's specifying what
exists in the literature and this took
some time because I was more on the
active inference like the free energy
principle side so I had to read more
about like Optimal control sarcastic
optimal control qmdps and understand
that in fact
what we're doing is simply adding more
structure on the latent space of of the
agent and the state space of the agent
and uh doing this allows to ask the
question like why is this useful why
having a state space that encodes
different perspectives so the motivation
comes from the Consciousness and study
cognitive Sciences but why it can be
useful for Robotics and it's always been
like my motivation study uh some
statistical statistical models more
structured models with more our priori
that can be useful uh for understanding
the behavior of a closed system like an
agent like a collection of neurons like
even like molecular machines okay so
that's a very long answer but it's okay
cool so you focused on the spatial
movement epistemic foraging case
is there something special about space
or can we also think about this
perspective taking in terms of for
example semantic or a narrative
reference frame
so the this is I think it's a very very
important question because up to now all
the work a reference will need to space
so the fact is based in terms of the 3D
space and not space in terms of geometry
and the fact of writing it as geometry
allows to get out from the classical
point of view as space as a 3D space
because you see that there's more and
more like for example in the in
geometric deep learning there's more and
more the use of uh space to encode
environments of certain objects and
these objects are not necessarily uh had
the three the three-dimensional
structure you can have objects that have
higher groups of ignorance so I think
that the
it's it's indeed using geometry for
other contexts and it's really the aim
of trying to go through this more
General formulation is to be able to
apply it to real world models what I
mean by real world models it means the
ones that are learned to be able to have
an agent in an open environment that
will learn the way uh it would learn its
generative model but with they are
priori that it can take a perspective on
its environment and see what it can do
so we really want to get out from the
3DS at least for me go out from 3D space
and go to like implementing it
completely in autonomous agents
okay to kind of follow on that there's a
question to chat great talk I also
wonder whether it applies to any
modality not just visual spatial but
also text
yeah so it's for other modalities like
sound for example what I don't know for
applying to text
so there's a lot of work now on uh large
language models and like of this idea of
prompting and being having these models
being able to have some kind of
imagination so you would like to have
this kind of these ideas applied in this
context but for now I mean it's not the
line that we're trying to that I'm
trying to do so I'm trying to stay on
deep learning so basically take standard
data set without considering uh uh like
text and just try to see how these ideas
like in geometric deep learning can
stabilize representations
so it's not the same that is a lot of
others it's clearly other modalities
especially if we consider like
multi-model integration like you you try
to rebuild the state space and you don't
want to see it only as a vector space
but you wanted to see it got more
structure because you want to force the
way like you have constraints be you
know appear only the constraints that
you're going to have on the way that you
can take a perspective on one volatility
or the other but it's not for text at
least not matter I think it maybe it
could be used for text but but it's not
what I'm doing now yeah
okay so it's I I I I just wanted to
rebound
I have the lack of collaborating with
real mathematics
some guy with intuition that I've found
the right people to to do the work uh
regarding multimodality this is
important to understand that this is not
about vision
this is about spatial recognition it's
supermodal the claim is that vision is
just one particular way of integrating
information indeed in an obviously
projective manner but that's integrated
in a much larger field of experience
than the field of view or the visual
field and obviously proprioception touch
when you build a representation just by
touching something and you get the 3D
representation of the scene
automatically in your mind hearing to
the extent that it's about Source
localization and building spatial uh uh
uh representation all of that stuff
that's the claim of the theory is
integrated in this projective space they
are priors from memories there are stuff
from Vision staff from addition stuff
from popular reception in the reception
you name it all senses contribute to it
so it's not Vision the claim is that
projective 3D projective geometry in
that case is beyond Vision vision is
just actually a slave to that Supreme
other representations that's the claim
um awesome all uh yeah please
that's important because we haven't
choose I think we like we let's say we
work like a group there are several like
different perspectives for me I'm more
on the computational side so it's
important to have that color because
clearly something I won't be able to
answer
cool here's a nice following question
from Vladimir in the chat they wrote
if the
EG visual sensors have variable
resolution for example higher resolution
in the center
this can naturally lead to curiosity
based change of orientation response
within your framework
so is it the question or an affirmation
so it's for EG right so if there's a
variable if there's variable sensor
Precision for example higher Precision
in the sensor might you see any
resulting
curiosity Associated change merely based
upon the asymmetry or the structure of
the sensor Fields okay so I shouldn't
say it but I will still say it because I
don't know if the people will go out one
day or nothing this is more attention
this is more attention than curiosity so
it's more like uh so you can act on your
sensors so that you can uh change the
way that you integrate them and this
really acts as a form of attention
so I really went into it
what do you think what is the interplay
between attention
and curiosity
uh
uh I mean
it's it's the way you're going to move
basically on the the way the way that it
deforms the way that you move that you
so the consequences of your actions are
not the same so basically curiosity is
what what drives actions and the way
that you uh said the con so you choose
your action with respect to reward which
is a epistemic value and now attention
or let's say changing the sensors is a
way to change the consequences of your
action with respect to let's say
optimizing this value so it's it's like
um
yeah I mean it's it's yeah I
I don't know if I should say yes or not
but okay okay let's say it's okay that's
it for I think it's symmetric basically
it's it acts like a sort of metric on
the space on the the group directly so
it means that it's going to so when you
have a function you want to degrade in
this engine you choose a metric and the
metric is so the attention will act as a
metric and so the metric will allow you
to deform in fact
um the the steps that you will do and so
I think this is how it acts so it's very
known that I mean it's known that the
fact that changing the sensors is is
related to attention that's not
something much new but the fact that you
can directly in our setting related to
groups and you can relate it to uh like
changing the metric on the group is
something that that can be done and I
think it's it's interesting
um all right another question in the
chat
what is a formal framework for learning
geometry from data
how do we move from empirical data sets
the files on our computers and the
things that we do deep learning on take
into machine learning pipelines and how
do we utilize geometric approaches and
formalize to the kind of analytical
Precision that we saw here some of these
geometric relationships
so the the there's a very like uh there
are several different fields of how to
use geometry uh on data so there's
already like I mean depends how you see
geometry but one way is a TDA
topological data analysis so which is
basically trying to uh let's say uh do
you want supervised learning by
geometric Pro like stability property of
of your data and try to interpret it as
a certain kind of space and then you
look at the whole of your space and this
is something that defines your data set
so this is one approach another one is
that people doing many like they try to
learn the so they they know that you're
that the that the data lives in the low
dimensional manifold and they try to
learn this manifold so that's another
perspective another way of doing it so
there's a lot of work in this in this
direction there are people who are
interested in variants and equivalence
so more in the geometric deep learning
there are people who are interested in
the same setting on appearance how to
use the geometric aprioris and included
in learning for a deep learning
reinforcement learning and this is what
we do in fact this is where one of where
many people do this it's not just then
we like for us we try to focus on this
idea of how to export it for
reinforcement learning
um so in this setting
epistemic value was the only driver of
action is that yeah so it's kind of like
a expected free energy
except without pragmatic value so we
only have the epistemic term remaining
exactly exactly in fact if you look at
in terms of optimal control and not by
Asian because you know that there's this
Duality that is most of the time stated
in like active influence where you have
basically a duality between the uh let's
say uh
about like a stochastic value function
and the probabilistic version of value
function so you can encode like on
priors you can encode all your drives
with priors or with uh the value
function directly so rewards and so both
are kind of dual and they're dual in the
way and you can make like this there's
Duality I mean it's I don't know if it
explicitly dual like in some context
this this sentence makes sense for
active inference for me I'm not
completely aware if the Duality is
exactly formal but at least this the
idea is here so there's no big
difference at least the way I see it as
with value function and seeing it
probabilistically but the terms of
epistemic value is a is a is an
exploration Drive which you also find in
reinforcement learning maybe not in this
exact expression I think that the exact
expression that was given in the paper
of a 37 and all is is
[Music]
is on the paper it's it's um it's
um it's a very uh uh like a canonical
way to define a epistemic value so it's
an exploratory drive you can always add
to the value function
you know that there's a lot of problem
of trying to explore in fact uh like
your environment you find the good
policies like it because if you're in a
state space that is continuous it's
really difficult to uh to result in p1bp
yes it's like if you knew which
Curiosities you could
get rewarded from
you would have already known the answer
to the search
so that's that's one of the
challenges with pragmatic value
it converges well to expectations but
then
this work uh really
focuses in on epistemic value and shows
what it can do alone as a driver
so how would you bring pragmatic value
into this formalism you just added you
just like it's really you can put the
value functions of some of the rewards
in some way and then you add and then
you add the epistemic value in fact when
you look at the formulation in terms of
belief and DP for pumdp the Curiosity
epistemic value is simply a value
function nothing more it's a one-step
value function but I mean this is like
just playing with definitions but so you
can always add a drive for uh for
exploration and this is something that's
really often done in uh in reinforcement
learning I mean I care
yes
like I think it's even standard in not
this way exact not exactly this
expression but there's a book that is
called reinforcement learning state of
the art and they they introduce this
exploratory Drive
like this is a book maybe that has 10
years or something like this so it's
something that you add up you can put
you can put your the way we will do it
now is like we we can we can put some
drawers or with respect to preferences
and then you add for example an
epistemic value and you try to to just
solve the optimization problem but like
in terms of formalism as you look at the
belief mdp it's nothing more than a
certain value function so it's not
foreign
so space
remains
when we translate through it
or when we
whether we're in the euclidean or in the
projective setting space is basically
the
what is not changed through action
is that the case okay
and so is that the weight so the so the
thing is that so okay so there's a bit
of technicality so the way that we use
it we use a chart so we need to take for
the protective plane so we need to use
homogeneous coordinates so we need to
take away a like a lower dimensional
plane
so that's why you always have the same
like in the the way that we encoded we
always are in R3 because we chose a
chart I mean we chose a homogeneous
coordinates and we use projective
Transformations from one homogeneous
coordinates to another homogeneous
coordinate but it always lists to a
Project X transformation so what is
hidden in the way that we write it is in
fact we don't have the same space in the
first case we have a Cleveland and the
second we have projective so but the way
as we use charts and we like I mean we
don't put all the details of
the fact that for example you can
compose two projective transformations
in uh by even if you write it in charts
in terms of homogeneous coordinates and
it stays a productive transformation
this is something that is okay but it's
it's we just don't write it this way we
stay in charts and so that's why there's
a similarity between e because we want
to implement it there's a similarity
between the acridian
projected case clear case and protective
case have the same state space R3 but
the space of transformation is really
different and in fact they are not the
same space but when it's important for
us in terms of spaces just to tell
yourself that if you take away
everything that is inside the space all
the all the like everything that
populates space you take it away what
what you're left with is with this kind
of Concepts which already takes into
account the fact that when you act
you're not changing you're not changing
the space and there's no single point
that is singled out so this is very
important because it's a very typical
like it types A lot of the objects
you're looking at like if you move
there's no point in the space that is
changing there's no point that it's
single out and when you move the space
it's not changing so you know that you
you already have inside of your space a
change of charts that is that is encoded
and even more when you can imagine that
you take the perspective of somebody
else
and this is like really something that
is at the basis of the space we consider
is that the space is simply a way to
support the fact that you can change
charts you can change perspectives and
so it's including this idea inside of
agency that we're trying to do so maybe
I was not clear in the way that I
installed it first but I think this is
really
opportunity
it's the water we're in so it's a very
interesting
um way to approach it and it reminds me
way back when actually almost three
years ago when we discussed the
projective Consciousness model and
phenomenal selfhood in live stream
number nine
and um
we talked a lot about
flipping between the euclidean and the
projective
modes how an agent could have on one
hand
a space in which
um
a book is a rectangle and yet also be
seeing it very close to their face so
that it's visual uh projection was was
different and yet here
there was different Behavior associated
with
the frame alone so what's going on there
where even though they
apparently can be reconstructed
from each other
what flips can we flip from thinking
more
euclidean and then in that situation
um you know I'm a plane 30 000 feet
above my city so there's nowhere I need
to go
but then in the projective setting
we do have this kind of inbuilt
epistemic drive to to be near
so I think it's it's a hard coded so so
the the idea is one of the things that
it can be useful for is communication so
using space as a way to communicate
taking an example that we have very
different architectures like the way
that we treat information are not the
same we don't have exactly the same
connection neurons and everything but we
still have like a common framework in
which we can discuss for example in a
visual visual information is something
that is very immediate for us which is
not obvious if you take the perspective
the point of view if you go from the
idea that it's rebuilt and it's not the
environment you're living on it's not in
it's not the exactly the space that we
see there's something that we
constructed like uh for uh like uh
functional reasons and that is one of
them could be that we can communicate
very directly with it so I think it's
hard coded that the state space needs to
have this action
and that all the agents share this
action but they don't share the same
architecture so it gives a common base
for discussion like true actions for
example change that of perspective so it
gives like the so it's the chance of a
question or clean projective we're not
going in the direction uh in terms of
research where we're trying to say that
we can go from a community to projective
for the same agent we so agents are
hard-coded with the latent space which
is a has some structure and then we try
to export it for function for
communication for multi-agent uh like uh
Behavior so that they can collaborate
this is
okay so each agent is within its own
projective setting and then the
euclidean
sets the stage and allows that
multi-perspective the oxygen space which
is the outside world is just here in
this toy model because we it's a way to
reference the configuration of the world
but for a network this would be for
example the configurations of its
sensors
so it's just here there's a there's this
kind of ambiguity between space and
space so outside space which is occasion
and inside which is projective but the
outside space is just a way to discuss
uh configurations of something that is
related to the environment so it can be
like your your sensors the configuration
of your sensors or something like this
information coming from your sensors so
you just give a state space from it and
the geometry is really in the
reconstructured world that is internal
but the being able that you do networks
that do this is somewhere that we're
working on now and it's not that obvious
because you need to there's a lot of
algorithms the problem algorithmic
problems that we try to solve and that
we need to solve so in the story Model
is really like the ambiguity comes only
from the fact that it's a toy model and
but what is space is inside it what is
reconstructed is the thing that we
perceive space from sensors as being a
whole as being something that structures
the information and so David wants to
say something or
well I mean yes indeed in the talk you
are having too I was giving them also
and it really felt if I remember well
yeah indeed the toy models encoded a
certain world model in an Acadian uh way
uh and then using homogeneous coordinate
and this kind of stuff to do the
projective uh transformation uh we just
transform the Acadian space into a
projective space
and you can go of course it's in you can
invert it I mean there is an online air
division but you can invert it anyway uh
so you can go from one to the other but
Gregor is right that it was a choice of
modeling it was a bit motivated by my
experiment my experience as a brain
scientist you know there are reasons to
believe that memory for instance Place
sales and grid cells they then do their
new hypothesis about their hyperbolic
characters but they you know usually
they are thought as encoding space in
the nuclearian manner so since when we
project uh you know future action we use
sometimes and we have to use memory or
even if we do a remembrance of the past
and we project ourselves in the scenes
in the past there is this access to
memory systems that you know we used to
think and probably this is still the
case on code information in a Korean
manner so it would make sense that then
for the conscious access there will be
some operation that would allow us to go
from the Cleveland to project which you
know was implemented that way at the
same time this is way beyond my my
abilities in math so regular will
correct me
there is a way of seeing projective
geometry as being more General as an
extension of a fine Space by adding
point at Infinity so if now you think
about the project space with a metric
basically uh the projective space is an
extension of a trillion space am I
saying something completely false
yeah I mean it's one way to sing it and
also a lot of operations that use
dialogues I would say exchange between
projective and Acadian if you think
about multi-view reconstruction of 3D
equipment space for multiple shots in
your camera you take several shots of a
building from different perspective and
then you can use a deterministic
algorithm I mean approach using people
are geometry to kind of infer under some
fires that basically all lines that
converge at Point at Infinity are
actually parallel then you reconstruct
you go from projective to euclidean so
there is a you know
a deep relationship between the two that
is possible and probably functional
um
yeah that's that's about it so and
people are geometry is a is a subset of
projective geometry no yeah so just to
leave some context
David has a better intuition on
protective spaces and me this is like
this so when he says stuff
I I I I like I I not he really has a
very uh
intuitive like physical personal like
visualization and most of the time he's
right so yeah
foreign
experiencing a projective geometry or
what is it like to experience a
projective geometry
so one one problem that there's this
with this model is the fact that you
have so you need to force the point that
Infinity to be um so the plane you take
away from the projected space has to be
behind and So you you're not really
working with real Maps you when no you
can always extend them that's okay but I
mean the thing is if you want to see it
in the way that we see it s which is we
have something in front of us I find it
a bit restrictive to say that you cannot
see what's behind you I mean you never
see it right I mean you can imagine it
which is not the same thing because you
change your frame so I can't answer
really this question I'm just pointing
out the fact that for me it's very
perturbating to think that I have a
plane that corresponds to uh this
continuity uh I mean with respect to I
mean I have a plane that destroys
completely the way that I can think
about movement behind me which is that
if I had to imagine I had the whole
space in that is around me and not just
in front of me things would be very very
weird in terms of Transformations but
it's not something that is not possible
possible I mean it's uh this is what
happens when you take psychiatric you
basically
allows the projective transformation
yeah like maybe you have all these
degrees of freedom but in the perception
like in some sorry motor processes this
is calibrated this is restricted so we
have to choose certain subset of the
group basically it's just it's only
certain project transformation that will
be used in practice but now if you go
into mystical experience or you take
drugs they are going to mess precisely
that's the hypothesis because with those
parameters and now you have the full
flight 15 degrees of freedom
transformation and you see things that
are very weird like that looks like
mandalas or things like that so that's
something you can get when you when you
leave too much freedom to the projective
action basically it's having yeah what
if what we're seeing quote in front of
us is behind us or something like that
what do you mean
what was the what was the issue with not
being able to see behind us the issue is
so if you want to see the project space
as a 3D space as a way that we skip now
need to take away your plane and
basically projective transformation so
that is sort of playing at Infinity on
which you can
I mean it doesn't exist in the projected
space it exists only in the way you
define the navigation chart like a 3D
like our R3 chart
uh with the plane that is taken away and
and so this plane that is behind you if
you apply a projective transformation
like in front of you everything will
seem fine you're You're Expecting like
it's things that you experience but then
once what happened is that it can send
things at the infinity back behind you
and so this is something that is a bit I
mean for me I'm very on on I mean it's
if I so you can write it explicitly
there's no problem mathematically but if
it's really the way that we experience
it it's extremely weird to think about
so I prefer not thinking about it so
this is the only thing I and I don't
think drugs so I'll leave it to other
people I mean it's really a good it's
true that taking drugs in this context
makes complete like you can you could
model it in the projective framework and
not in the euclidean framework because
you have a huge amount of protective
Transformations that make sense more
than the one that are related to actions
in there so in in the presentation I
give there was a way to relay attack
like a cleaning friends to protect the
frames under certain actions and in fact
you have a huge much bigger space of
projective Transformations than the one
that are restricted through by uh
the actions of the agents so the action
of the agent inside of the real space so
the occlusion space induced projective
transformation in its internal world but
there are much more projective
transformation than these actions and so
you can imagine in this setting having
like very confusing States uh of your
mind in a way it's really a good friend
like this
which you cannot in the application case
so
I wonder if if a creature with or a
robot with 360 degree cameras
would it not be so perplexed as it
wouldn't necessarily have a visual
before or a visual in front and behind
and the thing is how do you glue them
together
they still have to pick a point you
still have to pick a point of
convergence right I mean you need to you
need to find a way to do multi-modal
integration like if you if you want to
have a camera that's 360 uh you have if
you have the space to represent it so
maybe you can represent it as a sphere
and in this case the sense
the sensors the sensors are different so
it's it's not necessarily the same the
same robot than the models that we are
considering but there might be also
another homogeneous space so a g space
which is a space acting like which
corresponds to the rotations of the uh
of uh of uh like if you say that it can
look 360 and then you can rotate and the
space of observation stays the same so
you can always imagine acting on it and
so you can imagine like having another
g-space structure and the good thing
about it is just with respect to the
perspective if you have an agent that
can take a different perspective on this
environment which depends on its sensors
and its actions and the kind of data you
have then you can Define G space and you
can do exactly the same setting
everything like it's it's made in the
morals General more General context so
you can apply it and so it's not limited
only to the
projective case I like we come from the
PCM projective Consciousness model
but uh I mean the the framework now are
at least the way to replace this
framework inside of uh optimal control
is uh well adapted for any change of
perspective and nothing and not just
projective
awesome well
Where Are You Gonna
go to next where will the epistemic
drive take you
carrying forward
so that there are two projects now so
the first one is to be able to be like
have a maybe that we can talk but but is
to be able to uh to get uh so to
implement it so that it can be used for
uh monitoring behaviors or to be able to
predict behaviors or to analyze it so if
you have a model of behaviors of Agents
like maladaptive behaviors think that we
already published but in more limited
context now to make it inside of a
computational framework so that we can
use it to analyze like experiments with
humans so this is the first project
which is ongoing with several students
so on the page that I put on my on the
first slide there's all the work that
we're doing the people who are working
with us and we're very grateful for them
working with us and all the ongoing work
in this direction and there's the second
one which is more like say machine
learning and so for me it's very
important you have effective algorithms
things I mean like things that you can
really use in practice things that you
can really Implement and implementing
when you have group structures there are
many many problems that appear how to do
sarcastic optimal control when the
latent space is a homogeneous space it's
I think a completely open question when
I start you have answers in this
direction so I hope hopefully the the
work will go out come out soon let's say
uh January or something like this but
it's there's a huge work in this
direction
cool anything else you want to add
thank you very much for the invitation
[Music]
a lot to
think about Slash
mentally rotate slash project I mean
after all as you even alluded to with
communication
yeah this is a perspective taking
question
Technologies adding some new flavors and
methods
for example
asynchronous communication but it's
synchronous for the agent when they
perceive it but all these different
modalities of communication and
it's quite interesting to think about
and just really cool that you and
colleagues are pursuing that from
empirical
data analytic and from theoretical
mathematical approaches
I mean on this side for communication I
think and so it's something I I find
extremely interesting like more
generally if some people want to some
people want to work on the project
please tell us and I will be very happy
and if you and even if you have money
please tell us and who are very happy
here so
I agree
great great we were very open you can
always send us a mail we'll be very
happy to discuss about this week
okay well thank you again to to um all
till next time
okay
see ya bye bye